The last section of this chapter deals with the prostate.
A few basic principles before we move forward.
Of course, the prostate is a small round gland,
and it sits at the base of the bladder.
So here's the bladder, here's the prostate.
Running through the center of the prostate
is the urethra.
We call that the prostatic urethra.
And then the prostate sits anterior to the rectum.
And of course, that's important
because when we do a digital rectal exam,
we're able to palpate the posterior aspect of the prostate.
Histologically, the prostate consists of both glands and stroma.
The stroma represents the connective tissue,
and the glands represent the functional unit of the prostate.
Remember that the prostate secretes an alkaline milky liquid
that is added to the sperm and seminovesical fluid.
The glands of the prostate actually contain two layers.
There's a inner luminal layer and an outer basal cell layer.
And overall, both the glands and the stroma
are maintained by androgens.
The first disorder is acute prostatitis.
This is acute inflammation of the prostate,
usually due to bacteria.
The bacteria that are involved here
and the demographics are exactly the same
as those that we discussed in orchitis.
So that in young adults, chlamydia and neisseria
are the most common causes of acute prostatitis.
Whereas in older adults, the organisms that are usually
responsible for urinary tract infection, such as E. coli and pseudomonas,
are also the most important causes of acute prostatitis.
Patients with acute prostatitis present with pain during urination,
along with fever and chills.
On digital rectal exam, the prostate would be tender and boggy.
That's particularly high yield.
And the prostatic secretions would show white blood cells,
with the culture usually revealing bacteria.
Chronic prostatitis is chronic inflammation of the prostate.
It also presents with dysuria.
However, this is usually associated with pelvic or low back pain.
Again, here the prostatic secretions would also show white blood cells.
However, the cultures are usually negative.
BPH is benign prostatic hyperplasia.
This is hyperplasia of both the prostatic stroma,
as well as the glands.
It's an age-related change.
It's seen in most men by the age of 50.
Important to note that despite the fact that we call this hyperplasia,
there is no increased risk for cancer.
Now, I am particular about pointing this out because,
generally speaking, recall from chapter one,
that when you have pathologic hyperplasia,
that's classically a soil or a risk factor for the development of cancer.
However, in the case of benign prostatic hyperplasia,
there is no increased risk for cancer.
Very important to note this.
BPH is driven by DHT.
Recall that testosterone is converted to DHT by 5-alpha reductase in the stromal cells.
That DHT then acts on the androgen receptors of both the stromal and epithelial cells
to result in hyperplastic nodules.
It's important to note, and particularly high yield,
that BPH occurs in the periurethral zone of the prostate.
So that if I took the prostate on cross-section and the urethra is running through the center of it,
BPH occurs here, around the periurethral zone.
Now, that's particularly important because BPH will then result in compression of the urethra,
and most of the clinical features of BPH are all due to urinary obstruction.
For example, patients will have problems starting and stopping the urine stream.
Patients also experience impaired bladder emptying.
Again, recall that the prostate sits at the base of the bladder,
and running through the prostate, of course, is the urethra.
Now, BPH is occurring in the periurethral zone,
which is then obstructing the, which is then creating an obstruction,
and this will impair bladder emptying.
In addition, the bladder is going to have to press against that obstruction,
and so therefore the smooth muscle of the wall of the bladder will undergo hypertrophy.
It's also possible that the high pressure generated by the bladder as it pushes against the obstruction
could result in diverticuli, or outpouching, of the bladder wall.
So these are all, again, consequences of the fact that BPH occurs in the periurethral zone.
Patients can also experience dribbling, hypertrophy of the bladder wall smooth muscle,
as I've already stated, microscopic hematuria may be present,
and important to note that the PSA is often slightly elevated.
Now, the reason why the PSA is elevated is because PSA is produced by the prostatic glands,
and so if there are extra prostatic glands because there is hyperplasia,
there will be an increase in PSA as well.
But at the same time, it's important to note that this is only a slight elevation,
so that the normal PSA ranges from 0 to 4.
Generally speaking, in BPH, the PSA will range from anywhere from 4 to 10,
and this is considered a slight elevation in the PSA.
One of the complications of obstruction of the bladder is that you can also have subsequent
buildup of fluid backing up into the kidney, and when fluid backs up into the kidney because
it can't be drained, that's called hydronephrosis.
Of course, hydronephrosis results in dilatation of the ureter and can also result in dilatation
and atrophy of the kidney, and so this is an image of hydronephrosis.
There are multiple possible treatments for BPH.
One possibility would be to use alpha-1 antagonists, and this again would relax smooth muscle.
Now, the benefit of alpha-1 antagonists such as teresosin is not only do they relax the
smooth muscle to then relieve the obstruction of the prostate, but in addition, teresosin would
benefit the patient by relaxing the smooth muscle of the blood vessel wall, so that if
the patients are hypertensive, you sort of kill two birds with one stone.
If the patient happens to be normal-tensive, then a selective alpha-1A antagonist could
be used, such as tamulosin, which would avoid the alpha-1B effects on the vascular smooth muscle.
An additional pharmacologic treatment would be to use a 5-alpha reductase inhibitor.
Now recall that BPH is driven by DHT, and it's 5-alpha reductase that converts testosterone
to DHT.
Now the unfortunate thing about 5-alpha reductase inhibitors is that they usually take months
to produce results.
Prostatic adenocarcinoma is the last topic that we're going to discuss.
Again, adeno means gland, and carcinoma means malignant.
So this is a malignant proliferation of glands, of course involving the prostate.
Prostatic adenocarcinoma is the most common cancer in men, and it's the second most common
cause of cancer death.
Risk factors include age.
As a person ages, there's an increased risk for prostatic adenocarcinoma.
Race.
Prostatic adenocarcinoma has a higher incidence in African Americans.
Slightly beneath that is the incidence in Caucasians, and then slightly less than that is the incidence
in Asians.
So it's relatively more common in African Americans and less common in Asians.
And another risk factor is diets that are high in saturated fats.
Here's a cross section of the prostate.
Notice that the urethra runs through the center of the prostate.
Now it's important to note that prostatic adenocarcinoma, which is the lesion that I'm circling
here, occurs in the posterior periphery of the prostate.
Now the most common location for prostatic adenocarcinoma, again, is in the posterior periphery of the
prostate.
Now that's important because notice that it's very far away from the periurethra zone.
And so therefore, prostatic adenocarcinoma usually does not produce urinary symptoms
until very late.
Only if the cancer were to grow extensively and actually compress the periurethra zone would
you get urinary symptoms.
So generally speaking, prostatic adenocarcinoma is actually clinically silent and no urinary
symptoms are usually present.
Therefore, in order to detect prostate cancer, we need to screen.
And so screening begins at the age of 50 with both digital rectal exam and PSA.
Now recall that if this is the prostate here and it sits anterior to the rectum, then the
digital rectal exam is actually analyzing the exact location in which prostate cancer usually
occurs.
Because remember that prostate cancer usually arises in the posterior periphery of the
prostate.
An additional method of screening is the PSA.
The normal PSA ranges from anywhere from 0 to 4 nanograms per deciliter.
Now as patients age, that normal PSA can increase such that the range from 4 to 10 is sort of
a borderline number in which depending on the age, it may or may not be elevated for a particular
patient.
However, once the PSA gets to be above 10, that's highly worrisome at any age.
And so that would then prompt us to become particularly worried about prostate cancer.
Another way by which we can screen is to look at the free PSA in the serum.
Now generally speaking, cancer makes bound PSA so that a decrease in the percentage of free
PSA would be suggestive of cancer.
Now when the clinical suspicion is sufficient, then a prostatic biopsy will be performed.
And it's important to note that in order to make a diagnosis of cancer, this is required.
You cannot assume that the patient has cancer based on a high PSA or an abnormal digital
rectal exam.
So prostatic biopsy must be performed before the prostate would ever be removed.
On biopsy, we would classically see small glands that infiltrate the normal prostatic tissue.
And one of the high yield characteristics of prostate cancer is that the nuclei, which I'm
outlining here, contain these dark nucleoli.
Again, the nuclei contain these dark nucleoli.
And that's particularly characteristic for prostatic carcinoma.
The grading of prostate cancer occurs via the Gleason grading system.
Very high yield to note that the Gleason grading system is based on architecture alone.
And that nuclear atypia is not considered in the Gleason grading system.
In order to perform the grading, multiple regions of the tumor are assessed.
Now the reason for this is that there is high variability in the architecture of prostate cancer.
Or prostate cancer across the tumor.
So we actually have to look at multiple regions and then score different regions in order to
come up with a final score.
And this is classically done by looking at the two most common patterns that exist within
the cancer.
Those patterns are scored anywhere from one to five.
And then the two scores are added to produce a final score, which would range from two to
ten.
The higher the score, the worse the prognosis.
But again, the highest yield here is that the Gleason grading is based on architecture
and not nuclear atypia.
One of the important things about prostate cancer is that it often likes to spread to
the lumbar spine.
When it spreads to the lumbar spine, it produces osteoblastic metastases such that rather than
getting lytic punched out lesions, you get these sclerotic lesions of the bone.
Now this would present with low back pain and the alkaline phosphatase would be increased.
Again alkaline phosphatase is a sign of osteoblastic activity indicating that bone is being laid
down.
And we're well aware of the fact that we get osteoblastic metastases with prostate cancer.
In addition, we might see an elevation of PSA or the prostatic acid phosphatase, both of
which are serum tumor markers for prostate cancer.
Here's a picture of the osteoblastic metastases involving the lumbar spine.
And so you can see this area of sclerosis within the spine.
With local disease, prostate cancer is treated with prostatectomy.
So that is removal of the prostate.
If there is advanced disease, continuous GNRH analogs such as leuprolide can be used.
Now the idea here is that the GNRH analogs, when continuous, they shut down the hypothalamus,
which then reduces luteinizing hormone and FSH, which then in turn decrease the ability
of the prostate cancer to thrive because of course prostate cancer is androgen dependent.
In addition, we can use androgen receptor inhibitors such as flutamide, and again the notion here
is that prostate cancer is dependent on androgens in order to grow and thrive.
And that concludes both the section and this chapter.
Okay.
Thank you.
We'll see you next time.
Now let's see you next time.